I'll start with my favorite muse, Emily Dickinson,
سوف أبدأ بملهمتي المفضلة, اميلي ديكينسون
who said that wonder is not knowledge, neither is it ignorance.
التي قالت ان التساؤل لا يعتبر معرفة و لا هو جهل
It's something which is suspended
إنما هو شيء معلق
between what we believe we can be,
بين ما نؤمن بامكانية ان نكونه,
and a tradition we may have forgotten.
وتقليد قد نكون قد نسيناه.
And I think, when I listen to these incredible people here,
وإني أفكر, حين استمع لهؤلاء الاشخاص المذهلين هنا,
I've been so inspired -- so many incredible ideas, so many visions.
أنني ألهمت كثيرا....الكثير من الأفكار المذهلة...الكثير من الرؤى..
And yet, when I look at the environment outside,
ومع ذلك, حين انظر إلى البيئة الخارجية,
you see how resistant architecture is to change.
ترى كم تقاوم العمارة التغيير..
You see how resistant it is to those very ideas.
ترى كم تقاوم العمارة هذه الأفكار
We can think them out. We can create incredible things.
يمكننا ان نفكر بهم.  يمكن ان نبدع اشياء مذهلة .
And yet, at the end,
ولكن مع ذلك, في النهاية ,
it's so hard to change a wall.
من الصعب جدا تغيير جدار .
We applaud the well-mannered box.
نحن نستحسن الصندوق التقليدي المهذب
But to create a space that never existed is what interests me;
ولكن خلق فراغ لم يوجد من قبل هو مايستهويني
to create something that has never been,
ان تخلق شيئا لم يوجد من قبل
a space that we have never entered except in our minds and our spirits.
فراغ لم ندخله إلا في عقولنا وأرواحنا.
And I think that's really what architecture is based on.
واظن ان هذا هو في الحقيقة ما قامت عليه العمارة
Architecture is not based on concrete
العمارة ليست مبنية على الاسمنت .
and steel and the elements of the soil.
والحديد ومكونات التربة
It's based on wonder.
إنها مبنية على التساؤل
And that wonder is really what has created the greatest cities,
والتساؤل هو في الحقيقة ما خلق تلك المدن العظيمة
the greatest spaces that we have had.
اروع ما ملكنا من فراغات
And I think that is indeed what architecture is. It is a story.
واذن ان هذا هو حقيقة العمارة بالفعل . إنها قصة.
By the way, it is a story that is told through
و بالمناسبة...هي القصة التي تروى من خلال
its hard materials.
موادها الصلبة
But it is a story of effort and struggle
ولكنها أيضًا قصة من الجهاد والنضال
against improbabilities.
ضد الغير متوقع
If you think of the great buildings, of the cathedrals, of the temples,
إذا فكرت بالمباني العظيمة, بالكاتدرائيات, بالمعابد
of the pyramids, of pagodas,
بالأهرامات, بالباجودا (معبد بوذي متعدد الطوابق)
of cities in India and beyond,
بالمدن في الهند وغير ذلك
you think of how incredible this is that that was realized
تستطيع ان تدرك مدى روعة ما أنجز
not by some abstract idea, but by people.
ليس ببعض الأفكار المجردة, ولكن بـواسطة الأشخاص
So, anything that has been made can be unmade.
حسنا كل ما أنجز يمكن هدمه
Anything that has been made can be made better.
وكل ما أنجز..يمكن إنجازه بـشكل أفضل
There it is: the things that I really believe
هاهي الأشياء التي أؤمن بالفعل
are of important architecture.
انها تصف العمارة الهامة
These are the dimensions that I like to work with.
هذه هي الأبعاد التي أحب ان أعمل من خلالها
It's something very personal.
إنه شيء خاص جدا
It's not, perhaps, the dimensions appreciated by art critics
قد لا تكون هي ذاتها الأبعاد التي يقدرها نقاد الفن
or architecture critics or city planners.
أو نقاد العمارة أو مخططي المدن
But I think these are the necessary oxygen
و لكني أرى ان هذه تمثل الأكسيجن الضروري
for us to live in buildings, to live in cities,
لنا كي نعيش في المباني, كي نعيش في المدن
to connect ourselves in a social space.
كي نتواصل في فراغ اجتماعي
And I therefore believe that optimism is what drives architecture forward.
ولذا فـأنا أؤمن أن التفاؤل هو مايدفع العمارة للأمام
It's the only profession where you have to believe in the future.
هي المهنة الواحدة التي تتطلب منك أن تؤمن بالمستقبل
You can be a general, a politician, an economist who is depressed,
قد تكون لواء أو سياسي أو اقتصادي مكتئب
a musician in a minor key, a painter in dark colors.
أو موسيقي في نغمة منخفضة أو رسام بـألوان قاتمة
But architecture is that complete ecstasy that the future can be better.
ولكن العمارة هي تلك النشوة الكاملة ان المستقبل من الممكن ان يكون أفضل
And it is that belief that I think drives society.
وهي ذاك الإيمان الذي أؤمن أنه يقود المجتمع
And today we have a kind of evangelical pessimism all around us.
واليوم يوجد في كل مكان حولنا نوع من التفاؤل الانجيلي
And yet it is in times like this
ولكن انه في اوقات مثل هذه
that I think architecture can thrive with big ideas,
حين أظن ان العمارة تستطيع ان تزدهر بـأفكار جديدة
ideas that are not small. Think of the great cities.
أفكار ليست بـصغيرة..فكر بالمدن العظيمة
Think of the Empire State Building, the Rockefeller Center.
فكر بـمبنى الامباير إستات , بمركز روكيفيلر
They were built in times that were
قد تم بناؤها في اوقات
not really the best of times in a certain way.
لم تكون الأفضل بـشكل ما
And yet that energy and power of architecture
ولكن طاقة وقوة العمارة تلك
has driven an entire social and political space that these buildings occupy.
قد أوجدت فراغا اجتماعيا وسياسيا تشغله تلك المباني
So again, I am a believer in the expressive.
لذا وثانية....أنا مؤمن بـما هو معبر
I have never been a fan of the neutral.
لم أكون قط من مريدي ماهو حيادي
I don't like neutrality in life, in anything.
لا أحب الحياد في الحياة, في أي شيء
I think expression.
أنا أفكر بالتعبير
And it's like espresso coffee, you know, you take the essence of the coffee.
وهو مثل القهوة الاسبرسو. تأخذ فيها روح القهوة
That's what expression is.
هذا مثل التعبير
It's been missing in much of the architecture,
نفتقده من زمن في كثير من معمارنا
because we think architecture is the realm of the neutered,
لاننا نظن ان العمارة هي مملكة المحايدين
the realm of the kind of a state that has no opinion,
مملكة طبقة ما ليس لها رأي
that has no value.
ليس لها قيم
And yet, I believe it is the expression --
ولكن أنا اؤمن انه هو التعبير
expression of the city, expression of our own space --
التعبير عن المدينة, التعبير عن مساحتنا الخاصة
that gives meaning to architecture.
هو الذي يعطي معنى للمعمار
And, of course, expressive spaces are not mute.
وبالطبع فالمساحات المعبرة ليست صامتة
Expressive spaces are not spaces
المساحات المعبرة ليست تلك التي
that simply confirm what we already know.
تؤكد ببساطة مانعرفه سلفا
Expressive spaces may disturb us.
قد تزعجنا المساحات المعبرة
And I think that's also part of life.
وأنا أرى ان هذا جزء من الحياة
Life is not just an anesthetic to make us smile,
ليست الحياة مجرد مخدر كي نبتسم
but to reach out across the abyss of history,
ولكن لنعبر هاويات التاريخ
to places we have never been,
إلى أماكن لم نطأها من قبل
and would have perhaps been, had we not been so lucky.
أو كان من الممكن ان نراها لولا حظنا الحسن جدا!
So again, radical versus conservative.
لذا وثانية...الجذري في مقابل المحافظ
Radical, what does it mean? It's something which is rooted,
جذري , ماذا تعني؟ هو ما كان ضاربا في الأعماق
and something which is rooted deep in a tradition.
أو متأصل في التقاليد
And I think that is what architecture is, it's radical.
وهذا ما أظنه العمارة...هي جذرية
It's not just a conservation in formaldehyde
ليست حفظا في الفورمالدهايد
of dead forms.
لانماط ميتة
It is actually a living connection
هي في الحقيقة اتصال حي
to the cosmic event that we are part of,
بالحدث الكوني الذي نحن جزء منه
and a story that is certainly ongoing.
وقصة بالطبع مستمرة
It's not something that has a good ending or a bad ending.
ليست شيئا له بداية حسنة أو سيئة
It's actually a story in which our acts themselves
هي في الحقيقة قصة فيها افعالنا نفسها
are pushing the story in a particular way.
تدفع بالقصة في اتجاه معين
So again I am a believer in the radical architecture.
لذا وثانية أنا مؤمن بالعمارة الجذرية
You know the Soviet architecture of that building
تعلم؟ أسلوب العمارة السوفيتي لهذا المبنى
is the conservation.
هو التقليد المحافظ
It's like the old Las Vegas used to be.
مثلما كانت لاس فيجاس سابقا
It's about conserving emotions, conserving the traditions
انها المحافظة عن المشاعر ، والحفاظ على التقاليد
that have obstructed the mind in moving forward
التي أعاقت العقل أن يمضي قدما
and of course what is radical is to confront them.
وأعاقت بالطبع ما هو جذري لمواجهتها.
And I think our architecture is a confrontation
واعتقد ان عمارتنا هي مواجهة
with our own senses.
مع حواسنا الخاصة.
Therefore I believe it should not be cool.
لذا أعتقد أنه لا ينبغي أن تكون طريفة
There is a lot of appreciation for the kind of cool architecture.
فهناك الكثير من التقدير لهذا النوع من الهندسة المعمارية الطريفة
I've always been an opponent of it. I think emotion is needed.
لقد كنت دائما معارضا لذلك. وأعتقد أن هناك حاجة إلى العاطفة.
Life without emotion would really not be life.
الحياة بدون عاطفة لن تكون حياة
Even the mind is emotional.
حتى العقل عاطفي
There is no reason which does not take a position
فلا منطق أو سبب لا ياخذ مكانا
in the ethical sphere, in the philosophical mystery of what we are.
في الفضاء الأخلاقي أو المعضلة الفلسفية التي نحن فيها
So I think emotion is a dimension
لذا فأنا أرى ان العاطفة هي بعد
that is important to introduce into city space, into city life.
مهم يجب تقدمه لمحيط المدينة و حياتها
And of course, we are all about the struggle of emotions.
وبطبيعة الحال ، نحن جميعا نعيش النضال في العواطف.
And I think that is what makes the world a wondrous place.
وأعتقد أن هذا هو ما يجعل العالم مكانا رائعا
And of course, the confrontation of the cool, the unemotional with emotion,
وبالطبع ، فمواجهة الطريف اللاعاطفي مع العاطفي
is a conversation that I think
هي حوار اعتقد ان
cities themselves have fostered.
المدن ذاتها قد عززته
I think that is the progress of cities.
أعتقد أن هذا هو تقدم المدن.
It's not only the forms of cities,
ليس فقط نماذج المدن
but the fact that they incarnate emotions,
ولكن حقيقة أنها تجسد المشاعر ،
not just of those who build them,
ليس فقط للأشخاص الذين يبنونهـا
but of those who live there as well.
لكن لأولئك الذين يعيشون فيها أيضا
Inexplicable versus understood. You know, too often we want to understand everything.
الغير قابل للتفسير في مقابل المفهوم. تعلمون؟ كثيرا ما نريد أن نفهم كل شيء
But architecture is not the language of words.
ولكن العمارة ليست هي لغة الكلمات.
It's a language. But it is not a language that can be reduced
انها لغة. لكنها ليست اللغة التي يمكن اختزالها
to a series of programmatic notes that we can verbally write.
لسلسلة من الملاحظات المبرمجة التي يمكن أن تكتب بالألفاظ
Too many buildings that you see outside that are so banal
عدد كبير جدا من المباني التي تراها بالخارج والتي هي سخيفة جدا
tell you a story, but the story is very short,
تخبرك بـقصة ولكنى قصة قصيرة جدا
which says, "We have no story to tell you."
تقول... : "ليس لدينا قصة نرويها لكم".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the important thing actually,
لذا فالشىء الهام فعلا
is to introduce the actual architectural dimensions,
هو تعريف الأبعاد المعمارية الفعلية..
which might be totally inexplicable in words,
و التي قد لايمكن تفسيرها تماما بكلمات.
because they operate in proportions,
لأنها تعنى بالأبعاد
in materials, in light.
بالمواد ، بالضوء.
They connect themselves into various sources,
فهى تتصل بذاتها مكونة مصادر مختلفة
into a kind of complex vector matrix
مكونة نوعا ما من الفالب المتجهى المعقد
that isn't really frontal
و الذى ليس بحق ظاهرى
but is really embedded in the lives,
غير أنه مترسخ فى الحيوات
and in the history of a city, and of a people.
و تاريخ المدينة و تاريخ شعب.
So again, the notion that a building should just be explicit
مرة أخرى وهكذا ، فإن الفكرة القائلة بأن البناء ينبغي أن يكون واضحا و صريحا
I think is a false notion,
أعتقد أنها فكرة خاطئة ،
which has reduced architecture into banality.
أدت إلى تراجع العمارة في تفاهة.
Hand versus the computer.
اليد البشرية فى مقابل الكمبيوتر.
Of course, what would we be without computers?
بالطبع ، ما من شأنه أن نكون دون أجهزة الكمبيوتر؟
Our whole practice depends on computing.
ممارستنا كلها تعتمد على الكمبيوتر.
But the computer should not just be the glove of the hand;
ولكن ينبغي ألا يكون الكمبيوتر مجرد قفاز يد ،
the hand should really be the driver of the computing power.
وينبغي أن تكون اليد هى محرك القوة الحاسوبية
Because I believe that the hand
لأنني أعتقد أن اليد
in all its primitive, in all its physiological obscurity,
و بكل بدائيتها و بكل غموضها الفسيولوجى ،
has a source, though the source is unknown,
تحوى مصدرا ما ، على الرغم من أن هذا المصدر مجهول،
though we don't have to be mystical about it.
على الرغم من أننا لا يجب أن نتصوف فى هذا الأمر ،
We realize that the hand has been given us
ونحن ندرك أن اليد قد وهبناها
by forces that are beyond our own autonomy.
بواسطة قوى خارج نطاق حكمنا الذاتي..
And I think when I draw drawings
وأعتقد انه عندما أرسم رسومات
which may imitate the computer, but are not computer drawings --
قد تقلد الكمبيوتر ، ولكنها ليست رسومات بواسطة كمبيوتر
drawings that can come from sources
رسومات يمكن أن تأتي من مصادر
that are completely not known, not normal, not seen,
غير معروفة تماما ، غير طبيعية ، لم تر قط
yet the hand -- and that's what I really, to all of you who are working --
و لكن اليدة -- وبأن ما كنت حقا ، ولكم جميعا الذين يعملون --
how can we make the computer respond to our hand
كيف يمكننا ان نجعل الكمبيوتر يستجيب ليدنا
rather than the hand responding to the computer.
وليس أن تستجيب يدنا للكمبيوتر
I think that's part of what the complexity of architecture is.
اعتقد ان هذا جزء من تعقيد العمارة
Because certainly we have gotten used to the propaganda
ذلك أنه من المؤكد أننا قد اعتدنا على الدعاية
that the simple is the good. But I don't believe it.
بـأن ما هو بسيط هو جيد. لكنني لا أصدق ذلك.
Listening to all of you, the complexity of thought,
الاستماع الى كل واحد منكم ، وتعقد الفكر
the complexity of layers of meaning is overwhelming.
تعقد طبقات المعنى هو شيء غامر
And I think we shouldn't shy away in architecture,
وأعتقد أنه يجب ألا نخجل في الهندسة المعمارية
You know, brain surgery, atomic theory,
تعلمون ، جراحة الدماغ ، النظرية الذرية ،
genetics, economics
علم الوراثة ، والاقتصاد
are complex complex fields.
هي حقول معقدة تعقيدا شديدا
There is no reason that architecture should shy away
لا يوجد أي سبب أن تخجل العمارة
and present this illusory world of the simple.
أو ان تقدم عالما وهميا بسيطا
It is complex. Space is complex.
انه معقد. الفضاء معقد.
Space is something that folds out of itself into completely new worlds.
الفضاء هو شيء يفض طيات نفسه الى عوالم جديدة كلية.
And as wondrous as it is,
وعجيب كما هو،
it cannot be reduced to a kind of simplification
لا يمكن اختزاله إلى نوع من التبسيط
that we have often come to be admired.
اصبحنا نعجب به كثيرا.
And yet, our lives are complex.
فحياتنا معقدة.
Our emotions are complex.
مشاعرنا معقدة.
Our intellectual desires are complex.
لدينا رغبات فكرية معقدة.
So I do believe that architecture as I see it
لذلك أنا أعتقد أن فن العمارة كما أراه
needs to mirror that complexity in every single space that we have,
يحتاج أن يعكس هذا التعقيد في كل مسافة واحدة لدينا،
in every intimacy that we possess.
في كل علاقاتنا الحميمة بما حولنا
Of course that means that architecture is political.
بالطبع هذا يعني أن العمارة سياسية.
The political is not an enemy of architecture.
السياسي ليس عدوا للعمارة.
The politeama is the city. It's all of us together.
و ما هو  هو المدينة. انها نحن جميعا معا
And I've always believed that the act of architecture,
ولقد كنت دائما أرى أن العمل المعماري
even a private house, when somebody else will see it, is a political act,
حتى البيت الخاص ، عندما يراه شخص آخر ، هو عمل سياسي.
because it will be visible to others.
لأنه سيكون مرئيا للآخرين.
And we live in a world which is connecting us more and more.
ونحن نعيش في عالم يربط بيننا أكثر وأكثر.
So again, the evasion of that sphere,
مرة أخرى ، فالتهرب من هذا المجال
which has been so endemic to that sort of pure architecture,
التي كانت المستوطنة من أجل أن هذا النوع من الهندسة المعمارية الأصيلة
the autonomous architecture that is just an abstract object
العمارة المستقلة التي هي مجرد شيء مجرد
has never appealed to me.
لم ترق أبدًا لي
And I do believe that this interaction
وأعتقد أن هذا التفاعل
with the history, with history that is often very difficult,
مع التاريخ ، و الذي غالبا ما يكون صعبا للغاية ،
to grapple with it, to create
للتعامل معه، لخلق
a position that is beyond our normal expectations and to create a critique.
مكان يتجاوز توقعاتنا العادية وخلق نقد.
Because architecture is also the asking of questions.
لأن العمارة هي أيضا طرح الأسئلة.
It's not only the giving of answers.
انها ليست فقط في توفير الأجوبة
It's also, just like life, the asking of questions.
هى أيضا ، تماما مثل الحياة ، طرح الأسئلة.
Therefore it is important that it be real.
ولذل فمن المهم أن تكون حقيقية
You know we can simulate almost anything.
تعلمون أننا نستطيع محاكاة أي شيء تقريبا.
But the one thing that can be ever simulated
ولكن الشيء الوحيد الذي لا يمكن محاكاته أبدا
is the human heart, the human soul.
هو قلب الإنسان ، النفس البشرية.
And architecture is so closely intertwined with it
والهندسة المعمارية متشابكة بشكل وثيق معها
because we are born somewhere and we die somewhere.
لأنه في مكان ما ولدنا وسنموت في مكان ما.
So the reality of architecture is visceral. It's not intellectual.
لذا فواقع العمارة باطنى و ليس فكري.
It's not something that comes to us from books and theories.
انها ليست بالشيء الذى يأتي إلينا من الكتب والنظريات.
It's the real that we touch -- the door, the window,
انها حقيقية ، ونحن نلمسها ، الباب ، النافذة ،
the threshold, the bed --
العتبة ، السرير.
such prosaic objects. And yet,
تلك الأشياء العادية.و لكننى
I try, in every building, to take that virtual world,
أحاول ، في كل مبنى ، أن أتناول هذا العالم الافتراضي ،
which is so enigmatic and so rich,
الغامض جدا والغني جدا ،
and create something in the real world.
وخلق شيء في العالم الحقيقي.
Create a space for an office,
خلق مساحة للمكتب ،
a space of sustainability
مساحة مستديمة
that really works between that virtuality
تستطيع أن تجمع بين هذه الافتراضية
and yet can be realized as something real.
و يمكن أن تعتبر أيضا شيئا حقيقيا
Unexpected versus habitual.
الغير متوقع فى مقابل المعتاد.
What is a habit? It's just a shackle for ourselves.
ما هي العادة؟ انها مجرد تكبيل لأنفسنا.
It's a self-induced poison.
انها سم استحثناه بأنفسنا
So the unexpected is always unexpected.
فما هو غير متوقع هو دائما غير متوقع.
You know, it's true, the cathedrals, as unexpected,
تعلمون ، وهذا حقيقي ، الكاتدرائيات ، كما هوغير متوقع ،
will always be unexpected.
سوف تكون دائما غير متوقعة.
You know Frank Gehry's buildings, they will continue to be unexpected in the future.
تعلمون مباني فرانك جيري ، سوف تستمر في أن تكون غير متوقعة في المستقبل.
So not the habitual architecture that instills in us
فليست العمارة المعتادة هى التى تغرس فينا
the false sort of stability,
هذا النوع الكاذب من الاستقرار
but an architecture that is full of tension,
ولكن بنية مليئة بالتوتر ،
an architecture that goes beyond itself
بنية تتجاوز نفسها
to reach a human soul and a human heart,
للوصول إلى النفس البشرية وقلب الإنسان ،
and that breaks out of the shackles of habits.
متخلصة من أغلال العادات.
And of course habits are enforced by architecture.
وبالطبع العادات تفرضها الهندسة المعمارية.
When we see the same kind of architecture
عندما نرى نفس النوع من العمارة
we become immured in that world of those angles,
نصبح معتادين في هذا العالم من هذه الزوايا ،
of those lights, of those materials.
من تلك الأضواء ، من تلك المواد.
We think the world really looks like our buildings.
ونعتقد أن العالم يبدو حقا مثل مبانينا.
And yet our buildings are pretty much limited by the techniques and wonders
و لكن مبانينا هي الى حد كبير محدودة بالتقنيات والعجائب
that have been part of them.
و التى أصبحت جزءا منها.
So again, the unexpected which is also the raw.
مرة اخرى ، فالغير متوقع والذي هو أيضا الخام.
And I often think of the raw and the refined.
وأفكر أحيانا فى الخام والمكرر
What is raw? The raw, I would say
ما هو الخام؟ الخام ، أقول أنه
is the naked experience, untouched by luxury,
هو التجربة العارية ، لم تمسها يد الفخامة ،
untouched by expensive materials,
بمنأى عن المواد باهظة الثمن ،
untouched by the kind of refinement
بمنأى عن هذا النوع من التنقيح
that we associate with high culture.
الذى ربطناه بالثقافة العالية.
So the rawness, I think, in space,
لذا الغرور ، كما أعتقد ، في الفضاء ،
the fact that sustainability can actually, in the future
حقيقة أن الاستدامة يمكن -في الواقع- ، في المستقبل
translate into a raw space,
أن تترجم إلى مساحة خام
a space that isn't decorated,
مساحة غير مزخرفة ،
a space that is not mannered in any source,
مساحة لم تروض في أي مصدر
but a space that might be cool in terms of its temperature,
لكنها مساحة يمكن أن تكون باردة من حيث درجة الحرارة ،
might be refractive to our desires.
قد تعكس رغباتنا.
A space that doesn't always follow us
مساحة لا تتبع دائما لنا
like a dog that has been trained to follow us,
مثل الكلب الذي تم تدريبه على متابعتنا ،
but moves ahead into directions of demonstrating
ولكن يمضي قدما في اتجاهات تظهر
other possibilities, other experiences,
الاحتمالات الأخرى ، والتجارب الأخرى ،
that have never been part of the vocabulary of architecture.
التي لم تكن أبدا جزءا من المفردات المعمارية.
And of course that juxtaposition is of great interest to me
وبطبيعة الحال أن هذه المقاربة هي ذات أهمية كبيرة بالنسبة لي
because it creates a kind of a spark of new energy.
لأنه يخلق نوعا من شرارة الطاقة الجديدة.
And so I do like something which is pointed, not blunt,
وهكذا أحب شيئا حادا واضحا ، وليس بليد،
something which is focused on reality,
وهو أمر يركز على حقيقة واقعة ،
something that has the power, through its leverage,
الأمر الذي لديه السلطة ، من خلال نفوذه
to transform even a very small space.
لتحويل حتى مساحة صغيرة جدا.
So architecture maybe is not so big, like science,
الهندسة المعمارية قد لا تكون كبيرة مثل العلم ،
but through its focal point
ولكن من خلال نقطة الإتصال
it can leverage in an Archimedian way
فإنه يمكن الاستفادة بطريقة أرشميدية
what we think the world is really about.
ما نفكر به في العالم .
And often it takes just a building
وغالبا ما يتطلب الأمر مجرد بناء
to change our experience of what could be done, what has been done,
لتغيير خبرتنا في ما يمكن عمله ، ما تم إنجازه ،
how the world has remained both in between stability and instability.
كيف ظل العالم على حد سواء فى منتصف الاستقرار وعدم الاستقرار.
And of course buildings have their shapes.
وبطبيعة الحال فالمباني أشكالها.
Those shapes are difficult to change.
هذه الأشكال من الصعب تغييرها.
And yet, I do believe that in every social space,
وحتى الآن ، اعتقد أنه في كل فضاء اجتماعي
in every public space,
في كل مكان عام،
there is a desire to communicate more
هناك رغبة في مزيد من التواصل
than just that blunt thought, that blunt technique,
أكثر من مجرد هذة الخاطرة الفظة أو هذة التقنية البليدة
but something that pinpoints, and can point in various directions
ولكن الشيء الذي يبرز ، ويمكن أن يشير في اتجاهات مختلفة
forward, backward, sideways and around.
إلى الأمام ، الى الوراء ، فى الجنبات وما حول.
So that is indeed what is memory.
فهذا في الواقع ذاكرة [غير واضحة]
So I believe that my main interest is to memory.
لذلك اعتقد ان اهتمامي الرئيسي ينصب على الذاكرة.
Without memory we would be amnesiacs.
بلا ذاكرة سنعانى من نسيان مرضى.
We would not know which way we were going,
ولن نعرف أي طريق كنّا سالكيه،
and why we are going where we're going.
ولماذا نحن ذاهبون الى أين نحن ذاهبون.
So I've been never interested in the forgettable reuse,
لذا لم أهتم أبدا باعادة الاستخدام القابلة للنسيان،
rehashing of the same things over and over again,
اعادة لنفس الأشياء مرارا وتكرارا.
which, of course, get accolades of critics.
وهذا ، بالطبع ، والحصول على احتفاء النقاد
Critics like the performance to be repeated again and again the same way.
النقاد يحبون أن يتكرر الأداء مرة تلو المرة بنفس الطريقة.
But I rather play something
ولكنى أحب أن ألعب شيئا
completely unheard of,
لم يسمع به أحد بالكلية
and even with flaws,
وحتى مع عيوبه
than repeat the same thing over and over which has been hollowed
بدلا من تكرار الشيء نفسه مرارا وتكرارا مما أفقده
by its meaninglessness.
معناه
So again, memory is the city, memory is the world.
مرة أخرى وهكذا ، فالذاكرة هي المدينة والذاكرة هى العالم.
Without the memory there would be no story to tell.
بدون الذاكرة لن تكون هناك قصة تروى.
There would be nowhere to turn.
وسيكون هناك مكان نلتفت إليه
The memorable, I think, is really our world, what we think the world is.
و ما هو جدير بالتذكر، كما أعتقد ، هو حقا عالمنا ، ما نفكر أنه العالم.
And it's not only our memory,
وانها ليست فقط ذاكرتنا ،
but those who remember us,
لكن أولئك الذين يتذكروننا.
which means that architecture is not mute.
وهذا يعني أن العمارة ليست خرساء.
It's an art of communication.
إنها فن الاتصال.
It tells a story. The story can reach into obscure desires.
انها قصة. ويمكنها أن تصل إلى رغبات غامضة.
It can reach into sources that are not explicitly available.
ويمكن أن تصل إلى مصادر غير متوفرة بشكل صريح.
It can reach into millennia
ويمكن أن تصل إلى ألفيات
that have been buried,
ادفنت ،
and return them in a just and unexpected equity.
وتعيدهم في إنصاف غير متوقع
So again, I think the notion that
مرة أخرى وهكذا ، وأعتقد أن الفكرة القائلة بأن
the best architecture is silent has never appealed to me.
أفضل تصميم معماري هو الصامت لم ترق لي أبدا.
Silence maybe is good for a cemetery but not for a city.
الصمت هو ربما جيد للمقبرة ولكن ليس بالنسبة لمدينة.
Cities should be full of vibrations, full of sound, full of music.
ينبغي أن تكون المدن مليئة بالاهتزازات ، بالصوت ، بالموسيقى.
And that indeed is the architectural mission
وهذا هو في الواقع مهمة العمارة
that I believe is important,
و التى أعتقد أنها مهمة ،
is to create spaces that are vibrant,
أن تخلق المساحات الحيوية ،
that are pluralistic,
التعددية ،
that can transform the most prosaic activities,
التى يمكنها تحويل معظم الأنشطة العادية
and raise them to a completely different expectation.
و رفعها الى توقعات مختلفة تماما.
Create a shopping center, a swimming place
إنشاء مركز للتسوق أو مسبح
that is more like a museum than like entertainment.
أشبه بمتحف منه بمكان للترفيه .
And these are our dreams.
وهذه هي أحلامنا.
And of course risk. I think architecture should be risky.
وبطبيعة الحال خطرة. وأعتقد أن العمارة ينبغي أن تكون خطرة.
You know it costs a lot of money and so on, but yes,
وأنت تعرف أنها تكلف الكثير من المال وهكذا ، ولكن نعم
it should not play it safe.
فإنه لا ينبغي أن "تلعبها" بأمان.
It should not play it safe, because if it plays it safe
فإنه لا ينبغي أن "تلعبها" بأمان لأنه إذا فعلت
it's not moving us in a direction that we want to be.
الامور لن تسير بنا في الاتجاه الذي نريده أن يكون.
And I think, of course,
وأعتقد ، بطبيعة الحال ،
risk is what underlies the world.
أن الخطر هو ما يكمن وراء العالم.
World without risk would not be worth living.
سيكون العالم - من دون مخاطر- لا يستحق العيش.
So yes, I do believe that the risk we take in every building.
لذلك نعم ، أعتقد أن المخاطر التي نتخذها في كل مبنى.
Risks to create spaces that have never been cantilevered to that extent.
المخاطر لخلق المساحات التي لم تكن أبدا كابولية إلى هذا الحد.
Risks of spaces that have never been
مخاطر المساحات التي لم تكن أبدا
so dizzying,
مذهلة بهذا الشكل
as they should be, for a pioneering city.
كما ينبغي ، بالنسبة لمدينة رائدة.
Risks that really move architecture
المخاطر التي تحرك حقا العمارة
even with all its flaws, into a space which is much better
حتى مع كل عيوبها، الى فضاء أفضل بكثير
that the ever again repeated
من أي وقت مضى أن تتكرر
hollowness of a ready-made thing.
خواء الشيء الجاهز.
And of course that is finally what I believe architecture to be.
وبالطبع هذا هو في النهاية ما أعتقد أنه العمارة.
It's about space. It's not about fashion.
انه عن الفضاء. انها ليست حول الموضة.
It's not about decoration.
انها ليست حول الديكور.
It's about creating with minimal means
انها عن خلق- وبوسائل أدنى-
something which can not be repeated,
خلق أمر لا يمكن تكراره،
cannot be simulated in any other sphere.
لا يمكن محاكاته في أي مجال آخر.
And there of course is the space that we need to breathe,
وهناك بالطبع المساحة التي نحن بحاجة اليها للتنفس ،
is the space we need to dream.
المساحة التى نحتاجها للحلم.
These are the spaces that are
هذه هي الأماكن التي
not just luxurious spaces for some of us,
ليست فاخرة فقط للبعض منا ،
but are important for everybody in this world.
ولكن مهمة بالنسبة للجميع في هذا العالم.
So again, it's not about the changing fashions, changing theories.
مرة اخرى ، انها ليست حول الموضة المتغيرة، وتغيير النظريات.
It's about carving out a space for trees.
انها نحت مساحة للأشجار.
It's carving out a space where nature can enter
انها نحت حيث يمكن أن تدخل الطبيعة
the domestic world of a city.
الى العالم المألوف للمدينة.
A space where something which has never seen a light of day
الفضاء حيث الأمر الذي لم يسبق له أن رأى ضوء النهار
can enter into the inner workings of a density.
يمكنه الدخول في أعمال داخلية كثيفة.
And I think that is really the nature of architecture.
وأعتقد أن هذا هو حقا طبيعة العمارة.
Now I am a believer in democracy.
فأنا الآن مؤمن بالديموقراطية
I don't like beautiful buildings
فلا أحب المباني الجميلة
built for totalitarian regimes.
التي شيدت لأنظمة شمولية
Where people cannot speak, cannot vote, cannot do anything.
حيث لا يستطيع الناس ان يتكلموا , ان يصوتوا , لا يستطيعون ان يفعلوا شيئا
We too often admire those buildings. We think they are beautiful.
نحن غلبان ما نعجب بـتلك المباني, نظن انها جميلة
And yet when I think of the poverty of society
و لكن حين أفكر بفقر المجتمع
which doesn't give freedom to its people,
الذي لا يعطي لناسه الحرية
I don't admire those buildings.
لا أعجب بـهذه المباني
So democracy, as difficult as it is, I believe in it.
لذا فالديموقراطية على صعوبتها..أنا أؤمن بها
And of course, at Ground Zero what else?
وبطبيعة الحال ، في مكان البرجين وماذا ايضا؟
It's such a complex project.
انه لمشروع معقد
It's emotional. There is so many interests.
انه عاطفي. هناك مصالح كثيرة.
It's political. There is so many parties to this project.
انه سياسي. هناك أطراف كثيرة في هذا المشروع.
There is so many interests. There's money. There's political power.
هناك مصالح كثيرة. هناك المال. هناك سلطة سياسية.
There are emotions of the victims.
وهناك مشاعر الضحايا
And yet, in all its messiness, in all its difficulties,
وعلى الرغم من هذا، في كل فوضتها، في كل صعوباتها ،
I would not have liked somebody to say,
لم أكن أحب أن يقول شخص ما..
"This is the tabula rasa, mister architect -- do whatever you want."
"هذه أرض فضاء سيدي المعماري...افعل بها ماشئت"
I think nothing good will come out of that.
لا أعتقد أن شيئا جيدا سوف ينتج من ذلك.
I think architecture is about consensus.
أعتقد أن فن العمارة هو عن إجماع في الآراء
And it is about the dirty word "compromise." Compromise is not bad.
وانها تدور حول كلمة قذرة "حل وسط". الحل الوسط ليس بـسيئ
Compromise, if it's artistic,
الحل الوسط ، إذا كان فنيا
if it is able to cope with its strategies --
إذا كان قادرا على التعامل مع استراتيجياته--
and there is my first sketch and the last rendering --
وهذه مسودتي الأولى وتقدمها لليسار
it's not that far away.
ليس ببعيد
And yet, compromise, consensus,
فالحل الوسط ، والإجماع
that is what I believe in.
هو ما أؤمن به
And Ground Zero, despite all its difficulties, it's moving forward.
وأرض البرجين، على الرغم من الصعوبات التي تواجهها، تتحرك إلى الأمام
It's difficult. 2011, 2013. Freedom Tower, the memorial.
صعب. 2011 ، 2013. برج الحرية ، النصب التذكاري.
And that is where I end.
و هذا هو ما أنتهي عنده
I was inspired when I came here as an immigrant
ألهمت عندما جئت الى هنا كمهاجر
on a ship like millions of others,
على متن سفينة مثل ملايين آخرين ،
looking at America from that point of view.
أتطلع إلى أميركا من وجهة النظر هذه.
This is America. This is liberty.
هذه هي أميركا. هذه هي الحرية.
This is what we dream about. Its individuality,
هذا ما نحلم به. تفردها,
demonstrated in the skyline. It's resilience.
ظاهر في الأفق...مرونتها
And finally, it's the freedom that America represents,
وأخيرا ، انها الحرية التي تمثل أمريكا ،
not just to me, as an immigrant, but to everyone in the world. Thank you.
ليس فقط بالنسبة لي ، كمهاجر ، ولكن للجميع في العالم. شكرا لكم..
(Applause)
تصفيق
Chris Anderson: I've got a question.
كريس اندرسون : عندي سؤال
So have you come to peace
هل تسامحت
with the process that happened at Ground Zero
مع ما تم على أرض مبنى التجارة العالمي
and the loss of the original, incredible design that you came up with?
و فقدان التصميم الأصلي الرائع الذي استحدثته؟
Daniel Libeskind: Look. We have to cure ourselves
دانييل ليبسكيند : أنظر,يجب ان نداوي انفسنا
of the notion that we are authoritarian,
من نظرية أننا استبداديين
that we can determine everything that happens.
يمكننا تحديد كل مايحدث
We have to rely on others, and shape the process in the best way possible.
يجب ان نعتمد على الآخرين, وان نشكل العملية في أفضل شكل مممكن
I came from the Bronx. I was taught not to be a loser,
أنا نشأت في برونكس.تعلمت ألا أخسر
not to be somebody who just gives up in a fight.
ألا أكون مجرد شخص يستسلم في كل كفاح
You have to fight for what you believe. You don't always win
يجب ان تقاتل من أجل ما تؤمن به, لن تكسب دائما
everything you want to win. But you can steer the process.
كل ما أردت ان تكسبه..ولكن بـامكانك ان تقود العملية
And I believe that what will be built at Ground Zero
و أؤمن أن ما سيبنى على أرض مبنى التجارة
will be meaningful, will be inspiring,
سيكون ذا مغزى...سيكون ملهما
will tell other generations of the sacrifices,
سيخبر الأجيال الأخرى بالتضحيات
of the meaning of this event.
بمعنى هذا الحدث
Not just for New York, but for the world.
ليس فقط لمدينة نيويورك ,ولكن للعالم..
Chris Anderson: Thank you so much, Daniel Libeskind.
كريس اندرسون : شكرا جزيلا لك
(Applause)
تصفيق